Guide to the Alfred Hulse Brooks Photographs and Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Photographs and Other Work by Employees of the United States Geological Survey, 1898-1955; Series I; 4.42
  - Photographs by Unidentified Photographers
    - Locations
      - Fairbanks, circa 1900-circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 454-456)
      - Fort Gibbon, circa 1899-1923 (Box 5, Folder 457)
      - Glacier Bay, circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 458)
      - Gold Run, 1902 April (Box 5, Folder 459-461)
      - Happy Camp, circa 1937 (Box 5, Folder 462)
      - Healy Creek, circa 1918 (Box 5, Folder 463-464)
      - Hungry Creek, circa 1905 (Box 5, Folder 465)
      - Iliamna Lake, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 466)
      - Jualin, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 467)
      - Juneau, circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 468-469)
      - Ketchikan, circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 470)
      - Koyuk, circa 1905 (Box 5, Folder 471-472)
      - Nahk-ah-nahn, circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 473)
      - Nome, circa 1905 (Box 5, Folder 474)
      - Pilgrim River, circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 475)
      - Port Benny, circa 1925 (Box 5, Folder 476)
      - Seward, circa 1910-circa 1920 (Box 5, Folder 477-480)
        Includes views of the Burns Slough bridge on the Seward-Kenai Road and Snow River, as well as a portrait of guide Charles Emswiler with a large bear trophy.
      - Shungnak, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 481-487)
        Images include views of the Ruby Creek Copper Mine, and the mining operations on Dahl Creek of Louis Lloyd, Ase D. Wilcox, Frank Knight, and Thomas Shea.
      - Stillwater, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 488)
      - Susitna River, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 489)
      - Valdez, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 490)
      - Wainwright, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 491)
        Image of an Iñupiat celebration
    - Subjects
      - Boats and boating, circa 1900-circa 1940 (Box 5, Folder 492-506)
        Includes views of canoes and other ships, such as the sloop Gjøa, and several steamboats, including Beilby, Casca, Novelty, Queen, Senator, and Tyrrell.
      - Camps, circa 1905-circa 1940 (Box 5, Folder 507-513)
      - Horses, circa 1900-circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 514-518)
      - Indians of North America, circa 1905-circa 1930 (Box 5, Folder 519-521)
      - Landscapes, circa 1905-circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 522-529)
      - Mines and mineral resources, circa 1905-circa 1940 (Box 5, Folder 530-554)
        Images of mining operations include a dredger for the De Soto Placer Mining Company and a man at the opening of the Grotto Mine.
      - Transportation, circa 1905 (Box 5, Folder 555-557)
        Images of a railroad and draisines among snow drifts, as well as an automobile on Richardson Highway.
      - United States Geological Survey seal, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 558)
      - Wildlife, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 559-560)
        Consists of views of a salmon trap and a caribou herd.
    - Portraits, circa 1905-circa 1915 (Box 5, Folder 561-565)
      - Brooks, Alfred Hulse, circa 1900-circa 1917 (Box 5, Folder 566-568)
      - Collier, Arthur J., circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 569)
      - Graves, Lucy, circa 1940 (Box 5, Folder 570)
      - Griffin, C. L., circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 571)
      - Hess, Frank Lee, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 572)
      - Martin, George Curtis, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 573)
      - Mendenhall, Walter Curran, circa 1930 (Box 5, Folder 574)
      - Smith, Philip Sidney, circa 1935 (Box 5, Folder 575)
      - Unidentified portraits, 1912-circa 1920 (Box 5, Folder 576-579)
        Portraits include a man with a mammoth tusk and a Native American man with a large Chinook salmon
      - Group portraits, circa 1900-1917 (Box 5, Folder 580-593)
        Includes portraits of parties that accompanied Walter Lowrie Fisher, Secretary of the Interior, during his tour of Alaska in the summer of 1911, which include Alfred Hulse Brooks and Alaskan Governor Walter Eli Clark. Other identified individuals in group portraits include Frederick W. Hollender, Alexander Duncan McRae, Sidney Paige, and Philip Sidney Smith.
    - Enlargements and Mounted Photographic Prints
      - Locations
        - Anchorage, circa 1920 (Box 6, Folder 594)
        - Atlin and McKee Creek, British Columbia, circa 1905 (Box 6, Folder 595)
        - Cripple Creek, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 596-597)
          Views of a dragline excavator operated by the United States Smelting, Mining and Refining Company.
        - Disenchantment Bay and Turner Glacier (also known as Dalton Glacier) from Haenke Island, circa 1905 (Box 6, Folder 598)
        - Dominion Creek, British Columbia, circa 1900 (Box 6, Folder 599)
        - Harvard Glacier, circa 1900 (Box 6, Folder 600)
        - Hurricane Gulch and the Hurricane Bridge, circa 1920 (Box 6, Folder 601)
        - Kanalku Bay and the McCluskey Mine, circa 1900 (Box 6, Folder 602)
        - Kennicott and the Kennecott Copper Mine, 1919 (Box 6, Folder 603-608)
        - Kuskulana River and the North Midas Copper Company, 1919 (Box 6, Folder 609-612)
        - Lawing (also known as Roosevelt), circa 1925 (Box 6, Folder 613)
        - Lowe River, circa 1910 (Box 6, Folder 614)
        - Lurvey Basin (also known as Silver Bow Basin), circa 1905 (Box 6, Folder 615)
        - Nome, circa 1905 (Box 6, Folder 616-617)
        - Seward and the United States Revenue Cutter Tahoma, 1909-1915 (Box 6, Folder 618)
        - Saint Paul Island and a seal rookery, circa 1910 (Box 6, Folder 619)
        - Tanana River, Tanana River Bridge, and steamboat Martha Clow, circa 1925 (Box 6, Folder 620)
        - Willow Creek, circa 1910 (Box 6, Folder 621)
        - Yukon River near Nulato, circa 1910 (Box 6, Folder 622)
      - Subjects
        - Boats in a harbor, circa 1910 (Box 6, Folder 623)
        - Fourth of July celebration, 1910 July 4 (Box 6, Folder 624)
        - Horses and sleds, circa 1905 (Box 6, Folder 625-626)
        - Mining operations, circa 1905-circa 1910 (Box 6, Folder 627-630)
        - Totem pole, circa 1940 (Box 6, Folder 631)
      - Portraits
        - Alaska Railway Commission, 1912 November 19 (Box 6, Folder 632)
          Group portrait consisting of Alfred Hulse Brooks, Leonard M. Cox, Colin M. Ingersoll, and Jay Johnson Morrow.
        - Brooks, Alfred Hulse, circa 1895-circa 1917 (Box 6, Folder 633-636)
        - Schrader, Frank Charles, and Goodwill, circa 1900 (Box 6, Folder 637)
        - Copy photograph of an outline, "Alaska Mineral Resources: Principal Factors Controlling their Development", circa 1910 (Box 6, Folder 638)
  - Photographic Negatives and Transparencies
    - Film negatives, 2.25 x 3.25 inches, circa 1905 (Box 7, Folder 639-641)
      Images of donkeys and horses of a pack train.
    - Film negative, 5 x 7 inches, circa 1910 (Box 7, Folder 642)
      Aerial view of a lumberyard for a railway.
    - Copy photographs on glass negatives, 5 x 7 inches
      - Inupiaq, circa 1910 (Box 7, Folder 643-647)
        Includes a boy dressed in fur and holding harpoon; men hunting for seals among ice floes near Nome; an aerial view of a camp on a beach, and portraits of a man and a woman.
        Several of the original images were originally created by Lomen Brothers, Nome.
      - Steamship Victoria, circa 1910 (Box 7, Folder 648)
      - Sailing ship among ice floes, circa 1910 (Box 7, Folder 649)
    - Glass color transparency, 6.75 x 8.75 inches, circa 1935-1940 (Box 7, Folder 650)
      Cabin of miner and prospector Sam Means (born 1860) on May Creek near Chititu, probably created by Means.
- Photographs by Other Photographers, 1892-1936; Series II; 1.75
  Series II is organized into three subseries: Photographs by Identified Photographers, Photographs by Identified Photographers, and Panoramas.
  Photographs created by photographers and corporate bodies of sites and subjects chiefly in Alaska.
  - Photographs by Identified Photographers
    Organized alphabetically by the photographer or corporate body, followed by unidentified photographers, then by a small group of panoramas by Albert Barnes Kinne and McRae Brothers Limited
    - Alaska Central Railroad, 1903-1909 (Box 8, Folder 651-656)
      Images include views of railway tunnels and a rotary snow plow.
    - Alaska Engineering Commission, 1918-circa 1925 (Box 8, Folder 657-666)
      Many of the images were created by Henry G. Kaiser. Images of the Alaska Railroad include construction of the railway toward Turnagain, a trestle at Tunnel No. 1, and a railroad bridge over Tanana River. Images of boats include the Alaska Engineering Commission boat Betty M. on Susitna River and the Steamship Admiral Watson unloading freight at Knik. Other images include coal mines at Eska and gold mining operations in Chatanika.
    - Andrews, C. L., 1936 (Box 8, Folder 667-668)
      Images consist of views of Fairweather Mountain, Mount Crillon, and the LaPerouse Glacier.
    - Cameron, Guy Francis, circa 1920 (Box 8, Folder 669)
      Guy Francis Cameron (born 1874) was a photographer and tailor in Valdez.
      View of the Sheep Creek bridge on the Richardson Highway.
    - Century Syndicate, 1909 November (Box 8, Folder 670-696)
      The Century Syndicate was a publicity bureau established by the by the National Association of Manufacturers.
      Images chiefly of the Copper River and the surrounding region from the steamer Chitina and includes the Abercrombie Rapids, Allen Glacier, Baird Canyon, Mount Blackburn, Bremner River, Regal Mountain, Taral, and Wood Canyon. Other images include views of the Kennecott Copper Mine and a construction camp established by Michael J. Heney (1864-1910), a contractor for the Copper River and Northwestern Railway. Also includes an informal portrait Stephen Birch (1872-1940) a mining engineer and founder of Kennecott Copper. Accompanied by a list of captions.
    - Chapman, John Wight, 1916 April (Box 8, Folder 697)
      John Wight Chapman (1858-1939) was an Episcopalian missionary in Anvik from 1887 to 1930.
      Portrait of Ralph Wood of Anvik, an Ingalik berdache and specialist in fine bead and fur work.
    - Conradt, August William, circa 1940 (Box 8, Folder 698-704)
      August William Conradt (1878-1967) was a miner and insurance agent in Fairbanks.
      Images include Carl Tweiten and George Tweiten at the a gold claim in the vicinity of Ptarmigan Creek and views of Mount Hayes and Mount Hess.
    - Cook Inlet Exploration Expedition, 1898 June 29-October 23 (Box 8, Folder 705-712)
      Cook Inlet Exploration Expedition under the command of Captain Edwin Forbes Glenn (1857-1926) in south-central Alaska explored the country north of Cook Inlet to discover the most "direct and practicable" route from the coast to the Tanana River.
      Images include a group portrait of the expedition, interior and exterior views of the salmon cannery for the Pacific Steam Whaling Company at Prince William Sound; views of the steamer Salmo, and a group portrait of Native American men and others in a ship. Identified individuals include Lieutenant Joseph C. Castner, Walter Curran Mendenhall, Private George W. Van Schoonhoven, Private Adelbert L. Canwell, and guide Harry H. Hicks.
    - Curtis, Edward Sheriff, 1899 May-August (Box 8, Folder 713-714)
      Edward Sheriff Curtis (1868-1952) was a photographer known for his images of the American West and of Native Americans.
      Images of a glacier and a river created during the Harriman Alaska Expedition a maritime expedition sponsored by Edward Harriman to explore and document the Alaskan coast.
    - Davis, John, circa 1930 (Box 8, Folder 715)
      View of a rock strata on the bank of the Chickaloon River.
    - Dobbs, Beverly Bennett, circa 1906-1907 (Box 8, Folder 716-721)
      Beverly Bennett Dobbs (1868-1937) was a photographer in Bellingham, Washington, from 1888 until 1900, when he moved to Nome and continued his photography work. By 1903, he formed a partnership with the San Francisco photographer Albert Barnes Kinne (1853-1925). Around 1909, he established the Alaska Moving Picture Co. By 1911, Dobbs sold his photography negatives to the Lomen Brothers. Around 1914, he moved to Seattle and managed the Dobbs Totem Film Company.
      Images consist of the disparate mining operations of the Miocene Ditch Company, Three Friends Mining Company, and Topkok Ditch Company at Bluff and on the Solomon River.
    - Dunn, Robert Steed, 1900 July-1908 July (Box 8, Folder 722-769)
      Robert Steed Dunn (1877-1955) graduated from Harvard in 1898 and was an explorer, author, naval officer, and journalist.
      Photographs that document trips Dunn made with R. W. "Jack" Gray, probably Ralph Weld Gray (1880-1944), in the Wrangell Volcanic Field, July-August 1900, and Peters Glacier and Mount McKinley, July-September 1903, as well as views of the summit of Mount Wrangell made during an ascent he made with William Soule in 1908. Accompanied by a map created by Dunn and Gray of the Wrangell Volcanic Field, 1900.
      Some images illustrated articles Dunn published in Outing, an Illustrated Monthly Magazine of Recreation. These include "Finding a Volcano and Wiping a 16,000 feet Mountain from the Map of Alaska" (December 1902), "Into the Mists of Mt. McKinley" (February 1904), "Stormwrapped on Mt. McKinley" (March 1904), "Highest on Mt. McKinley" (April 1904), and "Home by Ice and By Swimming" (May 1904). Some images also illustrated his article, "Conquering Our Greatest Volcano: The First Ascent of Mount Wrangell, Alaska" in Harper's Magazine (March 1909).
      - Map of the Wrangell Volcanic Field, 1900 (Box 13, Folder 770)
    - Eglar, Joseph Henry, circa 1910-1915 (Box 9, Folder 771-779)
      Joseph Henry Eglar (circa 1870-1933) was a fisherman in Tacoma, Washington, and a miner in Alaska and the Yukon.
      Images of a gold and tin mining operation in Tofty.
    - Fassett, Harry Clifford, 1901 (Box 9, Folder 780-787)
      Harry Clifford Fassett (1870-1953) was joined the crew of the United States Fish Commission steamer Albatross in 1889 and kept its records until 1910. From 1911 to 1919, he represented the United States Bureau of Fisheries in Alaska.
      Images consist of views of Yakutat Bay and chiefly of the Hubbard Glacier.
    - Felch, Charles William, 1910 (Box 9, Folder 788-789)
      Charles William Felch was a photographer in Nome.
      Images consist of a pack train with supplies crossing Otter Creek at Flat and a mining operation at Otter Creek.
    - Hegg, Eric A., 1898-circa 1912 (Box 9, Folder 790-805)
      Eric A. Hegg (1867-1947) was a photographer active in Nome, Cordova, and the Yukon.
      Images consist chiefly of sites along the Copper River and Northwestern Railway including the Flag Point Bridge, the Miles Glacier Bridge, and the Steel Bridge over the Kuskulana River. Other images include emigrants at Chilkoot Pass in 1898 and a view of Chitina, as well as a group portrait of the Alaska Railway Commission, consisting of Colin M. Ingersoll, Alfred Hulse Brooks, Leonard M. Cox, and Jay Johnson Morrow.
    - Herning, Orville George, circa 1914 (Box 9, Folder 806-808)
      Orville George Herning (1868-circa 1947) represented the Klondike and Boston Mining Company in Knik from 1898-1905, and operated the Knik Trading Company from 1905-1917. He oversaw construction of the Klondike and Boston Trail from Knik to the Willow Creek Mining District (The Herning Trail). From 1917, he operated a general store in Wasilla.
      Images include men, horses, and wagons on a road as government surveyors arrive in Knik.
    - Hirschfeld, Alfred Cyril, 1899-1901 (Box 9, Folder 809-815)
      Alfred Cyril Hirschfeld (1866-1926) was a photographer in Atlin, British Columbia.
      Images of mining operations in British Columbia including the Atlin Mining Company on McKee Creek; the Société minière de la Colombie Britannique and the De Lamare Hydraulic Syndicate on Boulder Creek; and the Atlin Lake Mining Company in Atlin. There is also a view of the community of Discovery.
    - Hopkins, Grace Porter, 1900-1901 (Box 9, Folder 816-825)
      In 1893, Grace Porter Hopkins (born 1873) married Randolph D. Hopkins (born 1857), and they both worked in the United States Labor Department in Washington, D. C. She regularly contributed articles to newspapers and magazines, and authored The Economy Administration Cook Book (1913) with Susie Root Rhodes.
      Photographs possibly created by Alfred Hulse Brooks and collected by Porter, that document United States Geological Survey expeditions in Alaska. Images include an informal portrait of William John Peters and Walter Curran Mendenhall on the Fish River
    - Hunt, Harriet Elizabeth Frost, circa 1905 (Box 9, Folder 826)
      Harriet Elizabeth Frost Hunt (1865-1934) was married to Forest Joseph Hunt (1858-1947), a mayor of Ketchikan and member of the Alaska Senate. She was the first Republican National Committee woman from Alaska and a founder of the Ketchikan Public Library.
      View of the Copper Mount smelter, Coppermount, Prince of Wales Island.
    - Hunt, Phinney S., circa 1910-1912 (Box 9, Folder 827-830)
      Phinney S. Hunt (1866-1917) was a photographer in Valdez from 1898. In 1915, he became the official photographer for the Alaskan Engineering Commission.
      Images include trees at the Alaska Agricultural Experiment Station covered in ash from the eruption of Novarupta, a view of the Cliff Mine at Valdez Bay, A view of the Valdez-Fairbanks Trail outside lower end of Keystone Canyon, and a depiction of a man collecting ice worms from a glacier.
    - Isham, F. W., circa 1910-1915 (Box 9, Folder 831)
      View of rock fill from by the Resurrection Bay Mining Company from the steamer dock at Seward.
    - Johnson, Albert J., circa 1900-1912 (Box 9, Folder 832-840)
      Albert John Johnson (1874 or 1878-1926) emigrated to the United States from Denmark in 1886. He worked as a photographer in Fairbanks and Nenana, as well as Oakland, California.
      Postcards distributed by Johnson and Hall's Bookstore, a book store owned by Frank B. Hall in Fairbanks. Images chiefly depict Fairbanks, including L. F. Protzman Groceries, Nordale Hotel, McIntosh and Kubon Prescription Druggists, and the Alaska Agricultural Experiment Station, as well as a Fourth of July celebration and a visit by Santa Claus to Hall's Book Store. Other images include the coalfields of T. R. McGuire on the Nenana River and mining operations on Cleary Creek. Accompanied by an album with an inscription from Hall to Brooks, October 13, 1912.
    - Johnson, Frank Harold, 1942 July-1943 June (Box 9, Folder 841-865)
      Frank Harold Johnson (born 1894) was a businessman in Chicago with interests in Alaskan petroleum extraction.
      Images of petroleum drilling operations on the Nichawak River. Accompanied by correspondence between Harvey Charles Orton (1890-1961), a business engineer and consultant in Chicago, and Philip Sidney Smith about the images.
    - Johnson & Tyler, circa 1921-1922 (Box 9, Folder 866)
      Albert John Johnson and probably Andrew V. Tyler (born circa 1894) were photographers who worked together. Tyler also worked as a photographer with the United States Signal Corps in Valdez.
      View of the Healy River Coal Corporation mine at Healy.
    - Kaiser, Henry G., 1910-circa 1915 (Box 9, Folder 867-868)
      Henry G. Kaiser (born 1866) was a photographer in Nome, Anchorage, and Fairbanks, and an official photographer for the Alaska Engineering Commission.
      Copy photographs that consist of a view of a caribou herd at Sinook and a mining dredge.
    - Kaufmann & Fabry Co., 1921 October (Box 9, Folder 869-870)
      Kaufmann & Fabry Co. is commercial photography firm founded in 1903 by Charles Kaufmann and Herman Fabry in Chicago, Illinois.
      Images of the Alaska exhibit at the American Mining Congress annual meeting in Chicago, Illinois.
    - Keen, Dora, 1912 May-1913 January (Box 9, Folder 871-893)
      Dora Keen (1871-1963) was an American traveler and mountain climber, as well as a social social reformer and educator. She married George William Handy (1881-1982) on July 8, 1916; they divorced in 1932.
      Images document the first successful ascent of the eastern peak of Mount Blackburn (later called Mount Kennedy) in the Wrangell Mountains by Dora Keen and George W. Handy via the Kennicott Glacier in May 1912. Each image includes inscriptions in the negatives that describe the landscape and views.
      The photographs are accompanied by a two letters to Brooks from Keen, December 13, 1912, and January 31, 1913. They describe her ascent and request his assistance in identifying a mountain near Mount Blackburn.
    - La Roche, Frank, 1897-1898 (Box 10, Folder 894-898)
      Frank La Roche (1853-1936) was a photographer in Seattle, Washington. He made trips to southeastern Alaska and the Yukon Territory, especially during the Klondike gold rush.
      Images include views of Skagway, the Chilkoot Summit from Crater Lake, and the Klondike River.
    - LaVoy, Merl, 1912 (Box 10, Folder 899-902)
      Merl LaVoy (1886-1953) was a photographer, documentary film maker, and cameraman for Pathé News.
      Images consist of two men from the expedition of Herschel Parker and Belmore Browne en route up northeast ridge of Mount McKinley and men operating an electric drill at Copper Mountain (later called Mount Eielson), as well as views of Cape Saint Elias and miners near the Kuskulana River.
    - Logemann, William Ernest, circa 1920 (Box 10, Folder 903)
      William Ernest Logemann (1885-1952) was a photographer in Anchorage.
      View of the coal cleaning plant and tipple of the Evan Jones Mine at Jonesville.
    - Lomen Reindeer Corporation, circa 1938 (Box 10, Folder 904-905)
      Lomen Reindeer Corporation was a company headed by brothers, Carl Joys Lomen (1880-1965) and Alfred Julian Lomen (1889-1950) to market reindeer meat, 1914-1939. The Lomen brothers also operated a photographic firm that purchased studios and glass negatives of earlier Nome photographers, including Beverly Bennett Dobbs, and Frank H. Nowell; the building for this firm burned in 1934.
      Views of hybrid reindeer and caribou herds at Egavik.
    - Mack, Edward H., circa 1920 (Box 10, Folder 906-908)
      Edward H. Mack (1864-1935) was a clerk in the United States District Court in Fairbanks, as well as an insurance and real estate agent, and a Secretary and treasurers of the Fairbanks Commercial Club
      View of buildings at Chena Hot Springs.
    - Manger, Maximillian, 1919 (Box 10, Folder 909)
      Maximillian "Max" Manger (born 1874) was a commercial photographer in Fairbanks.
      Informal portrait of Alfred Hulse Brooks and John Hallowell, Assistant Secretary of the Department of the Interior, in a Ford automobile and an image of a crowd of men on a sidewalk in front of the Nordale Hotel in Fairbanks.
    - McRae Brothers Limited, circa 1920 (Box 10, Folder 910-911)
      McRae Brothers Limited was bookseller and stationery firm in Prince Rupert, British Columbia owned by Duncan C. McRae.
      View of the Zanardi River Bridge in Prince Rupert, British Columbia.
    - Means, Sam, circa 1920 (Box 10, Folder 912-913)
      Sam Means (born 1860) was a prospector and amateur photographer in Kennicott and May Creek.
      Images that depict the Kennecott Copper Mine at Kennicott, including the Jumble Mine.
    - Miller, N. B. and Charles Haskins Townsend, 1895 September 7 (Box 10, Folder 914-915)
      N. B. Miller (died 1897) was an assistant naturalist aboard the USS Albatross, a vessel manned by the United States Navy and assigned to the United States Fish Commission. Miller served aboard the USS Albatross for fourteen years preceding his death from